<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Posts on Ari Decter-Frain</title>
		<link>https://aridecterfrain.com/posts/</link>
		<description>Recent content in Posts on Ari Decter-Frain</description>
		<generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
		<lastBuildDate>Sat, 11 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
		<atom:link href="https://aridecterfrain.com/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
		<item>
			<title>Travel Map</title>
			<link>https://aridecterfrain.com/posts/ari-trips-toronto-london/</link>
			<pubDate>Sat, 11 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>https://aridecterfrain.com/posts/ari-trips-toronto-london/</guid>
			<description>I want to see as much of the world as possible while I can. The map I’m making here will serve as a reminder of the memories I made around the world, and as motivation to go out and see the rest.
I’ve made the map in Rmarkdown so anyone reading who has a basic familiarity with R and Rstudio should be able to easily make their own.
To make the map I used R, ggplot, and Google’s geolocation API.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[


<p>I want to see as much of the world as possible while I can. The map I’m making here will serve as a reminder of the memories I made around the world, and as motivation to go out and see the rest.</p>
<p>I’ve made the map in Rmarkdown so anyone reading who has a basic familiarity with R and Rstudio should be able to easily make their own.</p>
<p>To make the map I used R, ggplot, and Google’s geolocation API. I relied heavily on <a href="https://lucidmanager.org/create-air-travel-route-maps/">The Lucid Manager’s</a> post in which he creates his own.</p>
<hr>
<p>First loading all the necessary libraries</p>
<pre class="r"><code>suppressPackageStartupMessages({
  library(tidyverse)
  library(ggmap)
  library(ggrepel)
  library(maps)
  library(here)
})</code></pre>
<p>Here I’m setting internal filepaths. To reproduce the code below, replace the <code>here()</code> functions with the urls in the comments.</p>
<pre class="r"><code>path_flights &lt;- here(&quot;static&quot;, &quot;map&quot;, &quot;trips.csv&quot;)
#path_flights &lt;- &quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/aridf/travel-map/master/data/trips.csv&quot;
path_geos &lt;- here(&quot;static&quot;, &quot;map&quot;, &quot;geos.csv&quot;)
#path_geos &lt;- &quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/aridf/travel-map/master/data/geos.csv&quot;</code></pre>
<p>Loading the data. I had to add country info to some of the cities to ensure the google API searches for the correct city. I remove this later so it does not show up in my visualization.</p>
<pre class="r"><code>flights &lt;- read_csv(path_flights)
head(flights)</code></pre>
<pre><code>## # A tibble: 6 x 2
##   From       To         
##   &lt;chr&gt;      &lt;chr&gt;      
## 1 Bogota     Cartegena  
## 2 Cartegena  Guayaquil  
## 3 Cusco      La Paz     
## 4 Detroit    Minneapolis
## 5 Durham     Toronto    
## 6 Edingburgh London</code></pre>
<p>Here I’m deleting duplicates and return flights. This helps reduce the clutter in the visual.</p>
<pre class="r"><code>d &lt;- vector()
for (i in 1:nrow(flights)) {
    d &lt;- which(paste(flights$From, flights$To) 
               %in% paste(flights$To[i], flights$From[i]))
    flights$From[d] &lt;- &quot;R&quot;
}
flights &lt;- flights %&gt;%
  filter(From != &quot;R&quot;) %&gt;%
  select(From, To)</code></pre>
<p>Next, I grab coordinate data from the google API. I use two layers of conditions to limit the number of calls I’m making to the API. First, I check if I already have a list of locations and coordinates saved. If not, I get a list of all the locations in my flight list and call that API for each. If I already have some coordinates saved, I just check to see if there are any new locations. If there are, I call the API for the new entries only. If not, then I move ahead with my previous dataset.</p>
<pre class="r"><code>locations &lt;- unique(c(flights$From, flights$To))
if(file.exists(path_geos)) {
  geos &lt;- read_csv(path_geos)
  new &lt;- locations[!(locations %in% geos$airport)]
  if(length(new) &gt; 0) {
    geos &lt;- new %&gt;%
      geocode() %&gt;%
      mutate(airport = new) %&gt;%
      bind_rows(geos) %&gt;%
      select(airport, lon, lat)
    write_csv(geos, path_geos)
  }
} else {
  new &lt;- unique(c(flights$From, flights$To))
  geos &lt;- new %&gt;%
    geocode() %&gt;%
    mutate(airport = new) %&gt;%
    select(airport, lon, lat)
  write_csv(geos, path_geos)
}
head(geos)</code></pre>
<pre><code>## # A tibble: 6 x 3
##   airport       lon    lat
##   &lt;chr&gt;       &lt;dbl&gt;  &lt;dbl&gt;
## 1 Skagen      10.6   57.7 
## 2 Lisbon      -9.14  38.7 
## 3 Copenhagen  12.6   55.7 
## 4 Aarhus      10.2   56.2 
## 5 La Paz     -68.1  -16.5 
## 6 Bogota     -74.1    4.71</code></pre>
<p>Merging trip data and coordinates.</p>
<pre class="r"><code>flights &lt;- merge(flights, geos, by.x = &quot;To&quot;, by.y = &quot;airport&quot;)
flights &lt;- merge(flights, geos, by.x = &quot;From&quot;, by.y = &quot;airport&quot;)
head(flights)</code></pre>
<pre><code>##        From        To      lon.x     lat.x      lon.y     lat.y
## 1    Aarhus    Skagen  10.579186 57.725004   10.20392 56.162939
## 2    Berlin Marseille   5.369780 43.296482   13.40495 52.520007
## 3    Berlin     Milan   9.189982 45.464204   13.40495 52.520007
## 4    Bogota Cartegena -75.479426 10.391049  -74.07209  4.710989
## 5   Calgary  Winnipeg -97.138374 49.895136 -114.07085 51.048615
## 6 Cartegena Guayaquil -79.922359 -2.170998  -75.47943 10.391049</code></pre>
<p>Removing country info from the city names here.</p>
<pre class="r"><code>geos$airport &lt;- geos$airport %&gt;%
  word(1, sep = &quot;,&quot;)</code></pre>
<p>Creating my world map object. I’m setting the size limits of my map dynamically. This enables the map to expand dynamically as I travel to more regions of the world</p>
<pre class="r"><code>#set size limits of the worldmap. Prevent unvisited regions from displaying
xmin &lt;- min(geos$lon) - 10
xmax &lt;- max(geos$lon) + 10
ymin &lt;- min(geos$lat) - 10
ymax &lt;- max(geos$lat) + 10

#get map
worldmap &lt;- borders(&quot;world&quot;, xlim = c(xmin, xmax), ylim = c(ymin, ymax), 
                    colour = &quot;#eee8d5&quot;, fill = &quot;#eee8d5&quot;) </code></pre>
<p>This is the actual plot. The layers are pretty straightforward:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>geom_curve</code> creates curved lines connecting “From” and “To”.</li>
<li><code>geom_point</code> adds dots at each location</li>
<li><code>geom_text_repel</code> add labels while giving them room to breathe</li>
</ul>
<pre class="r"><code>ggplot() + worldmap + 
    geom_curve(data = flights, aes(x = lon.x, y = lat.x, xend = lon.y, 
                                   yend = lat.y), col = &quot;#2aa198&quot;, size = .4) + 
    geom_point(data = geos, aes(x = lon, y = lat), col = &quot;#268bd2&quot;) + 
    geom_text_repel(data = geos, color = &quot;#586e75&quot;, aes(x = lon, y = lat, label = airport), 
               col = &quot;black&quot;, size = 2, segment.color = NA, segment.size = 1) + 
    theme_void() +
    theme(panel.background = element_rect(fill = &quot;#fdf6e3&quot;))</code></pre>
<p><img src="/posts/ari-trips-toronto-london_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-9-1.png" width="4500" /></p>
<p>Finally, save out the file to a folder on my website so I can read it in as an image elsewhere.</p>
<pre class="r"><code>ggsave(
  filename = here(&quot;static&quot;, &quot;map&quot;, &quot;travel_map.png&quot;),
  width = 7.5,
  height = 4.5,
  units = &quot;in&quot;,
  dpi = 300
)</code></pre>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>How I Got To Cornell</title>
			<link>https://aridecterfrain.com/posts/ari-career-background/</link>
			<pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>https://aridecterfrain.com/posts/ari-career-background/</guid>
			<description>My career so far has been a delightfully eclectic adventure. In this post I provide a brief summary of my experiences and how they led me to start a PhD program at Cornell University.
1. University of Winnipeg 2012 - 2016 I completed my undergraduate degree in Psychology at the University of Winnipeg. While studying, I worked as a research assistant for different professors in the department. I worked most extensively in Dr.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[


<p>My career so far has been a delightfully eclectic adventure. In this post I provide a brief summary of my experiences and how they led me to start a PhD program at Cornell University.</p>
<div id="university-of-winnipeg" class="section level3">
<h3>1. University of Winnipeg</h3>
<div id="section" class="section level5">
<h5>2012 - 2016</h5>
<p>I completed my undergraduate degree in Psychology at the University of Winnipeg. While studying, I worked as a research assistant for different professors in the department. I worked most extensively in Dr. Jeremy Frimer’s Moral Psychology lab. I worked for two years as a research assistant. Then, during my final year, I took on my first leadership role as the lab’s manager. Our research used experiments and natural language processing to study:</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>The psychological differences between liberals and conservatives</li>
<li>The determinants of public approval of governing bodies, specifically US Congress</li>
<li>How leaders emerge and interact with social movements</li>
</ol>
<p>The unifying theme of our research was the rarity of fact-based decision-making. The field of political psychology identifies countless mechanisms that introduce bias to political and policy discourse. As I learned and contributed to this research, I came to view the scientific method as a critical asset in the war against bias. Through the application of scientific principles and rigorous research methods, we can ensure that evidence comes before ideology.</p>
<p>During this time I also worked as a researcher for the Public Interest Law Centre of Manitoba (PILC). I researched all sorts of topics to contribute to the 2016 Needs For and Alternatives To (NFAT) Review of Manitoba Hydro’s proposal to built two large hydroelectric dams in Northern Manitoba. The review took over a year. PILC played a key role in convincing the panel that the second dam carried too much risk to receive approval. Throughout the review, my assignments included:</p>
<ul>
<li>Reporting on the populations sizes, migration patterns and protection statuses of animal species native to the region surrounding the dams.</li>
<li>Learning and critiquing different approaches to cost-benefit analysis.</li>
<li>Summarizing and pulling key quotes from reports prepared by Manitoban Indigenous organizations.</li>
</ul>
<p>The NFAT proceedings renewed my optimism about evidence-based policy. The review involved collection and analysis of thousands of rows of data, consultation with dozens of academic experts, and tremendously thorough, creative analysis by the legal teams at PILC and Manitoba Hydro. In the end, the province made a (relatively) prudent decision not to invest in a high risk, long-term hydro-electric development. I longed for a world where more political discourse took this form.</p>
<p>After graduating I moved away from Winnipeg with a desire to develop my methods skillset and make data-driven contributions to the most important political debates of the day.</p>
<hr>
</div>
</div>
<div id="london-school-of-economics" class="section level3">
<h3>2. London School of Economics</h3>
<div id="section-1" class="section level5">
<h5>2016 - 2017</h5>
<p>I spent the next year in London, where I completed my MSc in Inequalities and Social Science. I learned how globalization and technological change have changed the labour market and produced rising income and wealth inequality in high-income countries.</p>
<p>LSE presents all kinds of opportunities to learn and have new experiences. I tried to take on as many as I could. I:</p>
<ul>
<li>Attended public lectures each week</li>
<li>Took methods courses from some of the world’s leading social scientists</li>
<li>Served as team leader for a student consulting project</li>
<li>Travelled, for work and play, to countries across Europe</li>
<li>Took my first coding course and fell completely in love with it</li>
<li>Made lifelong friendships with the members of my brilliant, inspiring cohort</li>
</ul>
<p>For my dissertation I used ten years of national UK survey data to analyze precarious employment among migrant workers. I found that migrants’ likelihood of experiencing precarious work conditions matched up with the historical and policy context surrounding their migration. For instance:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Migrants from outside the European Union were the most likely to work overtime. This makes sense, since these workers depend on the sponsorship of their employer to continue residing in the UK.</p></li>
<li><p>Migrants from a group of eight Eastern European countries flooded into the UK after their home countries joined the EU in 2002. Contrary to the widespread characterization of these migrants as lazy welfare scroungers, they are actually the least likely group to be unemployed, and among the most likely to work precarious jobs.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>Throughout the year at LSE I gained exposure to the full scope and diversity of opportunities I had. I graduated feeling encouraged to expect more from myself and from my life.</p>
<hr>
</div>
</div>
<div id="multi-health-systems" class="section level3">
<h3>3. Multi Health Systems</h3>
<div id="section-2" class="section level5">
<h5>2017 - 2019</h5>
<p>Next, I moved to Toronto and joined Multi Health Systems as a research analyst in their Innovation Hub, the company’s internal startup. In this role I did mostly data science work and developed my coding skills.</p>
<p>After 10 months I became a product manager. I led a small team working on feature updates for the products in our portfolio. I also developed a business model for the company’s new product line in the workplace health and wellness market.</p>
<p>From this experience I learned a tremendous amount about business decision-making, including how to:</p>
<ul>
<li>Decide which projects to develop internally and which to outsource</li>
<li>Build and analyze product PnLs</li>
<li>Package products and services together to create value for customers</li>
<li>Lead teams and motivate people</li>
</ul>
<p>I enjoyed the challenge of creating a sustainable business model and providing value for customers. I also gained a deeper appreciation for the role of the private sector in generating innovation.</p>
<p>I also saw how the same social scientific tools that I had come to view as essential for good policy could also help in the world of business. All manner of business decisions, from how to design a website to how to structure a business model, could be informed through the right kinds of data collection and experimentation.</p>
<p>I enjoyed my time at MHS. After a little less than two years, I felt ready to move on. I saw that I needed and achieve mastery over the methods I had come to worship as tools for making good decisions.</p>
<p>I chose to join Cornell’s Policy Analysis and Management program because it provides a unique level of freedom to take PhD level courses in Public Policy, Economics, and Sociology and develop specialization in any of these areas depending on how my interests develop.</p>
<p>As I move forward, I will continue seeking new and unique opportunities to promote truth and good science.</p>
</div>
</div>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>Agent-Based Modelling as a Tool to Advance Evolutionary Population Theory</title>
			<link>https://aridecterfrain.com/posts/cd_readinglist/bavel_grow_2016/</link>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>https://aridecterfrain.com/posts/cd_readinglist/bavel_grow_2016/</guid>
			<description>By Jan Van Bavel and André Grow, 2016 This article serves as the introduction to the book Agent-based modelling in population studies, edited by Bavel and Grow. Besides previewing the contributions made in the rest of the book, the authors discuss three important overarching topics:
1. Demography is “rich in methods, but poor in theories” Bavel and Grow describe the historical development of demography as a discipline that primarily serves governments by meticulously tracking populations for policy purposes.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[
<script src="/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js"></script>


<div id="by-jan-van-bavel-and-andré-grow-2016" class="section level2">
<h2>By Jan Van Bavel and André Grow, 2016</h2>
<hr />
<p>This article serves as the introduction to the book <em>Agent-based modelling in population studies</em>, edited by Bavel and Grow. Besides previewing the contributions made in the rest of the book, the authors discuss three important overarching topics:</p>
<div id="demography-is-rich-in-methods-but-poor-in-theories" class="section level3">
<h3>1. Demography is “rich in methods, but poor in theories”</h3>
<p>Bavel and Grow describe the historical development of demography as a discipline that primarily serves governments by meticulously tracking populations for policy purposes. As a result, they argue, the field has become mostly dominated by research using national samples to document trends. Relatively less work has gone towards theorizing the individual-level mechanisms that produce those trends, because such work is not valued unless it ties back to nationally representative data. They argue, like Billari over a decade earlier, that agent-based modelling is the key to pushing forward theory, because simulations based on these models can show how macro-scale trends emerge from individuals interacting according to theoretically-determined sets of constraints.</p>
</div>
<div id="the-macro-micro-macro-model" class="section level3">
<h3>2. The macro-micro-macro model</h3>
<p>The authors present the following diagram to describe the mechanisms in which demographers are interested:</p>
<p><img src="/misc_img/macro-micro-macro.png" /></p>
<p>Step 1 describes how individuals are affected by their surroundings. For instance, how one’s neighborhood of birth affects their life expectancy. Step 2 describes how individuals make decisions under external constraints, like deciding when to marry or how many children to have. Step 3 is the hardest to study. It describes how macro-level trends emerge from individual decisions. Bavel and Grow present agent-based modelling as a useful tool for carrying out this step, given that steps 1 and 2 have been carefully carried out for the question at hand.</p>
</div>
<div id="the-problem-of-validation" class="section level3">
<h3>3. The problem of validation</h3>
<p>A key challenge for agent-based modelling is demonstrating that these models are more than just “good stories”. Bavel and Grow outline a common argument that agent-based models can be made to produce any results if their parameters are set in just the right way. They propose propose the agent-based models are no more susceptible to this problem than any other type of statistical model. Moreover, they emphasize that agent-based models are meant to be used alongside empirical data in research. The can serve as guides for identifying important measures prior to conducting an empirical exercise. If the model itself is central to a researcher’s argument, they should be able to muster a range of empirical findings, both central and tangential to the model, that it match with the model’s expected outputs.</p>
<hr />
<div id="some-of-my-thoughts" class="section level4">
<h4>Some of my thoughts…</h4>
<p><em>Obvious parallels exist between the macro-micro-macro model and structural models in economics:</em></p>
<p><em>Models of supply and demand describe mathematically how individuals respond to prices and how their responses, in aggregate, determine how much of a good is consumed and produced. In a sense, this model is a generalization of the theoretical tools of economics beyond price mechanisms. This generalization is required, presumably, because price mechanisms can’t explain demographic and social phenomenon like fertility and migration.</em></p>
<p><em>In contrast to economic models which tend to be analytically solvable, we may only learn the outcomes complex agent-based models via simulation. However, economic models should still set the bar for validation. We should be able to see the trends that agent-based models predict in the same way that economists have long validated models of supply and demand.</em></p>
<p><em>Demography seems to lack well-established agent-based models for connecting these three steps. A potential exception is the Schelling model of neighborhood segregation, although even this has received criticism for its simplicity.</em></p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>billari_zagheni_2017</title>
			<link>https://aridecterfrain.com/posts/cd_readinglist/billari_zagheni_2017/</link>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>https://aridecterfrain.com/posts/cd_readinglist/billari_zagheni_2017/</guid>
			<description>R Markdown This is an R Markdown document. Markdown is a simple formatting syntax for authoring HTML, PDF, and MS Word documents. For more details on using R Markdown see http://rmarkdown.rstudio.com.
When you click the Knit button a document will be generated that includes both content as well as the output of any embedded R code chunks within the document. You can embed an R code chunk like this:</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[
<script src="/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js"></script>


<div id="r-markdown" class="section level2">
<h2>R Markdown</h2>
<p>This is an R Markdown document. Markdown is a simple formatting syntax for authoring HTML, PDF, and MS Word documents. For more details on using R Markdown see <a href="http://rmarkdown.rstudio.com" class="uri">http://rmarkdown.rstudio.com</a>.</p>
<p>When you click the <strong>Knit</strong> button a document will be generated that includes both content as well as the output of any embedded R code chunks within the document. You can embed an R code chunk like this:</p>
<pre class="r"><code>summary(cars)</code></pre>
<pre><code>##      speed           dist       
##  Min.   : 4.0   Min.   :  2.00  
##  1st Qu.:12.0   1st Qu.: 26.00  
##  Median :15.0   Median : 36.00  
##  Mean   :15.4   Mean   : 42.98  
##  3rd Qu.:19.0   3rd Qu.: 56.00  
##  Max.   :25.0   Max.   :120.00</code></pre>
</div>
<div id="including-plots" class="section level2">
<h2>Including Plots</h2>
<p>You can also embed plots, for example:</p>
<p><img src="/posts/cd_readinglist/billari_zagheni_2017_files/figure-html/pressure-1.png" width="672" /></p>
<p>Note that the <code>echo = FALSE</code> parameter was added to the code chunk to prevent printing of the R code that generated the plot.</p>
</div>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>Computational Demography Reading List</title>
			<link>https://aridecterfrain.com/posts/cd_readinglist/</link>
			<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>https://aridecterfrain.com/posts/cd_readinglist/</guid>
			<description>I put together this reading list as part of a guided reading with Professor Matthew Hall. We intend it to function as an overview of the field and as a syllabus for a graduate seminar. The list broadly covers the use of new data sources and agent-based modelling to advance our understanding of population and sociocultural processes.
Computational social science and demography  (Summary) Billari, F., and Zagheni, E.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[
<script src="/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js"></script>


<p>I put together this reading list as part of a guided reading with Professor Matthew Hall. We intend it to function as an overview of the field and as a syllabus for a graduate seminar. The list broadly covers the use of new data sources and agent-based modelling to advance our understanding of population and sociocultural processes.</p>
<div id="computational-social-science-and-demography" class="section level2">
<h2>Computational social science and demography</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>(<a href="billari_zagheni_2017/">Summary</a>) Billari, F., and Zagheni, E. (2017). Big data and population processes: a revolution? Proceedings of the Italian Statistical Society 2017 (Summary)</p></li>
<li><p>(<a href="bavel_grow_2016/">Summary</a>) Bavel, J.V., and Grow, A. (2016). Introduction: Agent-based modelling as a tool to advance evolutionary population theory. In eds. Bavel, Grow, Agent-based modelling in population studies (Summary)</p></li>
<li><p>Mario Molina and Filiz Garip. (2019). “Machine Learning for Sociology.” Annual Reviews of Sociology 45: 27-45.</p></li>
</ul>
</div>
<div id="social-media-and-demographic-processes" class="section level2">
<h2>Social media and demographic processes</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Zagheni E., Garimella, K., Weber, I., and State, B. (2014). Inferring international and internal migration patterns from Twitter data. Proceedings of ACM WWW (Companion): 439-444</p></li>
<li><p>Zagheni, E., Weber, I., &amp; Gummadi, K. (2017). Leveraging Facebook’s Advertising Platform to Monitor Stocks of Migrants. Population and Development Review, 43(4), 721-734.</p></li>
<li><p>Bruch, Elizabeth and Mark Newman. (2018). “Aspirational Pursuit of Mates in Online Dating Markets.” Science Advances, 4</p></li>
<li><p>Yildiz, D., Munson, J., Vitali, A., Tinati, R., &amp; Holland, J. A. (2017). Using Twitter data for demographic research. Demographic Research, 37(1), 1477–1514. <a href="https://doi.org/10.4054/DemRes.2017.37.46" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.4054/DemRes.2017.37.46</a></p></li>
</ul>
</div>
<div id="representativeness-of-social-media-data" class="section level2">
<h2>Representativeness of social media data</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Zagheni, E., &amp; Weber, I. (2015). Demographic research with non-representative internet data. International Journal of Manpower, 36(1), 13–25. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1108/IJM-12-2014-0261" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1108/IJM-12-2014-0261</a></p></li>
<li><p>Wang, W., Rothschild, D., Goel, S., &amp; Gelman, A. (2015). Forecasting elections with non-representative polls. International Journal of Forecasting, 31(3), 980–991. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijforecast.2014.06.001" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijforecast.2014.06.001</a></p></li>
<li><p>Gil-Clavel, S., &amp; Zagheni, E. (2019). Demographic differentials in facebook usage around the world. Proceedings of the 13th International Conference on Web and Social Media, ICWSM 2019, Icwsm, 647–650.</p></li>
<li><p>Feehan, D. M., &amp; Cobb, C. (2019). Using an online sample to estimate the size of an offline population. Demography, 2377–2392. <a href="https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1007/s13524-019-" class="uri">https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1007/s13524-019-</a> 00840-z)</p></li>
<li><p>Alexander, M., Polimis, K., &amp; Zagheni, E. (2020). Combining social media and survey data to nowcast migrant stocks in the United States. Population Research and Policy Review, 0123456789. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11113-020-09599-3" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1007/s11113-020-09599-3</a></p></li>
</ul>
</div>
<div id="social-media-data-in-low-income-countries" class="section level2">
<h2>Social media data in low-income countries</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Blumenstock, J.E., Cadamuro, G and On, R. (2015) Predicting Poverty and Wealth from Mobile Phone Metadata. Science, 350:1073-1076</p></li>
<li><p>Rampazzo, F., Zagheni, E., Weber, I., Testa, M. R., &amp; Billari, F. (2018). Mater certa est, pater numquam: What can facebook advertising data tell us about male fertility rates? 12th International AAAI Conference on Web and Social Media, ICWSM 2018, 672–675.</p></li>
</ul>
</div>
<div id="simulating-population-processes" class="section level2">
<h2>Simulating population processes</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Billari, F.C., Fent, T., Prskawetz, A., &amp; Scheffran, J. (2006). Agent-based computational modelling: An introduction. In eds. Billari, Fent, Prskawetz, Scheffran, Agent-based computational modelling: Applications in demography, social, economic and environmental sciences.</p></li>
<li><p>Hilton, J. and Bijak, J. (2016). Design and analysis of demographic simulations. In eds. Bavel, Grow, Agent-based modelling in population studies.</p></li>
<li><p>Williams, N.E., O’Brien, M.L. (2016). Using survey data for agent-based modelling: design and challenges in a model of armed conflict and population change. In eds. Bavel, Grow, Agent-based modelling in population studies.</p></li>
<li><p>Grow, A. (2016). Regression metamodels for sensitivity analysis in agent-based computational demography. In eds. Bavel, Grow, Agent-based modelling in population studies.</p></li>
<li><p>Wolfson M., Gribble, S., &amp; Beall, R. (2016). Exploring contingent inequalities: Building the theoretical health inequality model. In eds. Bavel, Grow, Agent-based modelling in population studies.</p></li>
<li><p>Kashyap, R., &amp; Villavicencio, F. (2016). The Dynamics of Son Preference, Technology Diffusion, and Fertility Decline Underlying Distorted Sex Ratios at Birth: A Simulation Approach. Demography, 53(5), 1261–1281. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s13524-016-0500-z" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1007/s13524-016-0500-z</a></p></li>
</ul>
</div>
<div id="agent-based-modelling-and-neighborhood-choice" class="section level2">
<h2>Agent-based modelling and neighborhood choice</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Bruch, E. E., &amp; Mare, R. D. (2006). Neighborhood choice and neighborhood change. American Journal of Sociology, 112(3), 667–709. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1086/507856" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1086/507856</a></p></li>
<li><p>Van de Rijt, A., Siegel, A., &amp; Macy, M. W. (2009). Neighborhood chance and neighborhood change: A comment on Bruch and Mare. American Journal of Sociology, 114(4). <a href="https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1086/588795" class="uri">https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1086/588795</a></p></li>
<li><p>Bruch, E. E., &amp; Mare, R. D. (2009). Preferences and pathways to segregation: Reply to Van de Rijt, Siegel, and Macy. American Journal of Sociology, 114(4). <a href="https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1086/597599" class="uri">https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1086/597599</a></p></li>
<li><p>Clark, W. A. V., &amp; Fossett, M. (2008). Understanding the social context of the Schelling segregation model. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America, 105(11), 4109–4114. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0708155105" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0708155105</a></p></li>
<li><p>Bruch, E. E., &amp; Mare, R. D. (2012). Methodological Issues in the Analysis of Residential Preferences, Residential Mobility, and Neighborhood Change. Sociological Methodology, 42(1), 103–154.https://doi.org/10.1177/0081175012444105</p></li>
</ul>
</div>
<div id="labor-markets" class="section level2">
<h2>Labor markets</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Turrell, A., Speigner, B. J., Djumalieva, J., Copple, D., &amp; Thurgood, J. (2019). Transforming Naturally Occurring Text Data Into Economic Statistics: The Case of Online Job Vacancy Postings. NBER Working Paper Series, 34. <a href="http://www.nber.org/papers/w25837" class="uri">http://www.nber.org/papers/w25837</a></p></li>
<li><p>Baker, R. S., Bloom, N., &amp; Davis, S. (2016). Measuring economic policy uncertainty. Quarterly Journal of Economics, 131(November), 1593–1636. <a href="https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1093/qje/qjw024" class="uri">https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1093/qje/qjw024</a></p></li>
<li><p>Lukac, M., &amp; Grow, A. (2020). Reputation systems and recruitment in online labor markets: insights from an agent-based model. Journal of Computational Social Science, 0123456789. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s42001-020-00072-x" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1007/s42001-020-00072-x</a></p></li>
<li><p>Subbotin, A., &amp; Aref, S. (2020). Brain drain and brain gain in Russia: Analyzing international migration of researchers by discipline using scopus bibliometric data 1996-2020. ArXiv, 49(May), 0–26.</p></li>
</ul>
</div>
<div id="migration" class="section level2">
<h2>Migration</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Deville, P., Linard, C., Martin, S., Gilbert, M., Stevens, F.R., Gaughan, A.E., Blondel, V.D. and Tatem, A.J. (2014) Dynamic Population Mapping Using Mobile Phone Data. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences 111(45):15888-15893.</p></li>
<li><p>Phillips, D. C. (2020). Measuring Housing Stability With Consumer Reference Data. Demography, 57(4), 1323–1344. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s13524-020-00893-5" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1007/s13524-020-00893-5</a></p></li>
<li><p>Palmer, J.R.B., Espenshade, T.J., Bartumeus, F., Chung, C.Y., Ozgencil, N.E., and Li K. (2012). New Approaches to Human Mobility: Using Mobile Phones for Demographic Research. Demography(50):1105-1128.</p></li>
<li><p>Fiorio, L., Zagheni, E., Abel, G., Hill, J., Pestre, G., Letouzé, E., &amp; Cai, J. (2020). Analyzing the Effect of Time in Migration Measurement Using Geo-referenced Digital Trace Data. 49(May), 0–41. <a href="https://doi.org/10.4054/MPIDR-WP-2020-024" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.4054/MPIDR-WP-2020-024</a></p></li>
</ul>
</div>
<div id="sociocultural-processes" class="section level2">
<h2>Sociocultural processes</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Marquez, N., Garimella, K., Toomet, O., Weber, I. G., &amp; Zagheni, E. (2019). Segregation and Sentiment: Estimating Refugee Segregation and Its Effects Using Digital Trace Data. Guide to Mobile Data Analytics in Refugee Scenarios, 49(0), 265–282. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-12554-7_14" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-12554-7_14</a></p></li>
<li><p>Stewart, I., Flores, R. D., Riffe, T., Weber, I., &amp; Zagheni, E. (2019). Rock, rap, or reggaeton?: Assessing Mexican immigrants’ cultural assimilation using Facebook data. The Web Conference 2019 - Proceedings of the World Wide Web Conference, WWW 2019, 3258–3264. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/3308558.3313409" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1145/3308558.3313409</a></p></li>
<li><p>Herdaǧdelen, A., State, B., Adamic, L., &amp; Mason, W. (2016). The social ties of immigrant communities in the United States. WebSci 2016 - Proceedings of the 2016 ACM Web Science Conference, 78–84. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/2908131.2908163" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1145/2908131.2908163</a></p></li>
<li><p>Gil-Clavel, S., Zagheni, E., &amp; Bardone, V. (2020). Close Social Networks among Older Adults : The Online and Offline Perspectives. 49(October), 0–25.</p></li>
<li><p>Dimaggio, P., &amp; Garip, F. (2012). Network effects and social inequality. Annual Review of Sociology, 38, 93–118. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.soc.012809.102545" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.soc.012809.102545</a></p></li>
</ul>
</div>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
