<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ari Decter-Frain</title>
    <link>https://aridecterfrain.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Ari Decter-Frain</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 11 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://aridecterfrain.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Travel Map</title>
      <link>https://aridecterfrain.com/posts/ari-trips-toronto-london/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aridecterfrain.com/posts/ari-trips-toronto-london/</guid>
      <description>I want to see as much of the world as possible while I can. The map I’m making here will serve as a reminder of the memories I made around the world, and as motivation to go out and see the rest.
I’ve made the map in Rmarkdown so anyone reading who has a basic familiarity with R and Rstudio should be able to easily make their own.
To make the map I used R, ggplot, and Google’s geolocation API.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How I Got To Cornell</title>
      <link>https://aridecterfrain.com/posts/ari-career-background/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aridecterfrain.com/posts/ari-career-background/</guid>
      <description>My career so far has been a delightfully eclectic adventure. In this post I provide a brief summary of my experiences and how they led me to start a PhD program at Cornell University.
1. University of Winnipeg 2012 - 2016 I completed my undergraduate degree in Psychology at the University of Winnipeg. While studying, I worked as a research assistant for different professors in the department. I worked most extensively in Dr.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About me</title>
      <link>https://aridecterfrain.com/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aridecterfrain.com/about/</guid>
      <description>I am a PhD student in Cornell’s Policy Analysis and Management program. During the summer of 2020 I served as a Data Science for Social Good Fellow at the University of Washington’s eScience Institute. I hold an MSc in Inequalities and Social Science from the London School of Economics and a BA in Psychology from the University of Winnipeg. I have also worked for two years as a data scientist and product manager at a people analytics firm called Multi Health Systems Inc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Agent-Based Modelling as a Tool to Advance Evolutionary Population Theory</title>
      <link>https://aridecterfrain.com/posts/cd_readinglist/bavel_grow_2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aridecterfrain.com/posts/cd_readinglist/bavel_grow_2016/</guid>
      <description>By Jan Van Bavel and André Grow, 2016 This article serves as the introduction to the book Agent-based modelling in population studies, edited by Bavel and Grow. Besides previewing the contributions made in the rest of the book, the authors discuss three important overarching topics:
1. Demography is “rich in methods, but poor in theories” Bavel and Grow describe the historical development of demography as a discipline that primarily serves governments by meticulously tracking populations for policy purposes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>billari_zagheni_2017</title>
      <link>https://aridecterfrain.com/posts/cd_readinglist/billari_zagheni_2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aridecterfrain.com/posts/cd_readinglist/billari_zagheni_2017/</guid>
      <description>R Markdown This is an R Markdown document. Markdown is a simple formatting syntax for authoring HTML, PDF, and MS Word documents. For more details on using R Markdown see http://rmarkdown.rstudio.com.
When you click the Knit button a document will be generated that includes both content as well as the output of any embedded R code chunks within the document. You can embed an R code chunk like this:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Computational Demography Reading List</title>
      <link>https://aridecterfrain.com/posts/cd_readinglist/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aridecterfrain.com/posts/cd_readinglist/</guid>
      <description>I put together this reading list as part of a guided reading with Professor Matthew Hall. We intend it to function as an overview of the field and as a syllabus for a graduate seminar. The list broadly covers the use of new data sources and agent-based modelling to advance our understanding of population and sociocultural processes.
Computational social science and demography  (Summary) Billari, F., and Zagheni, E.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>extra_text</title>
      <link>https://aridecterfrain.com/extratext/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aridecterfrain.com/extratext/</guid>
      <description>Through policy, governments set the rules of the game that all firms and workers play. I want to change the rules so that the game gives fairer rewards and everyone has a more equal chance at success.
Why do people flock to major cities despite ever-rising costs of living? Why is competition declining across industries? How did elite education become a necessary and sufficient condition for economic success?
Answering these questions requires accessing new kinds of data, revealing hidden social networks, identifying causal mechanisms, and understanding economic incentives.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>https://aridecterfrain.com/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aridecterfrain.com/research/</guid>
      <description>Computational Demography I think of computational demography as encapsulating the measurement and analysis of demographic processes via non-traditional data sources and computationally intensive methods. Professor Matthew Hall and I have developed a reading list for the field, available here.
My current work in this field is a collaboration with professors Matthew Hall and Arthur Acolin. We are evaluating potential contribution of consumer reference data for the measurement of small-area populations.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>