<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ari Decter-Frain</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Ari Decter-Frain</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 11 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Travel Map</title>
      <link>/posts/ari-trips-toronto-london/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/ari-trips-toronto-london/</guid>
      <description>I want to see as much of the world as possible while I can. The map I’m making here will serve as a reminder of the memories I made around the world, and as motivation to go out and see the rest.
I’ve made the map in Rmarkdown so anyone reading who has a basic familiarity with R and Rstudio should be able to easily make their own.
To make the map I used R, ggplot, and Google’s geolocation API.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How I Got To Cornell</title>
      <link>/posts/ari-career-background/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/ari-career-background/</guid>
      <description>My career so far has been a delightfully eclectic adventure. In this post I provide a brief summary of my experiences and how they led me to start a PhD program at Cornell University.
1. University of Winnipeg 2012 - 2016 I completed my undergraduate degree in Psychology at the University of Winnipeg. While studying, I worked as a research assistant for different professors in the department. I worked most extensively in Dr.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About Me</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>I am a PhD student in Cornell’s Policy Analysis and Management program. I hold an MSc in Inequalities and Social Science from the London School of Economics and a BA in Psychology from the University of Winnipeg. Before starting at Cornell, I worked for two years as a data scientist and product manager at the people analytics firm Multi Health Systems Inc. I have experience in computational social science, product management, and team leadership.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>extra_text</title>
      <link>/extratext/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/extratext/</guid>
      <description>Through policy, governments set the rules of the game that all firms and workers play. I want to change the rules so that the game gives fairer rewards and everyone has a more equal chance at success.
Why do people flock to major cities despite ever-rising costs of living? Why is competition declining across industries? How did elite education become a necessary and sufficient condition for economic success?
Answering these questions requires accessing new kinds of data, revealing hidden social networks, identifying causal mechanisms, and understanding economic incentives.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>